Chapter 115.
The Peekquad meets the Bachelor.
And jolly enough were these sights and sounds that came bearing down before the
wind some few weeks after Ahab's harpoon had been welded. It was a Nantucket
ship, the Bachelor, which had just wedged in her last cask of oil and
bolted down her bursting hatches, and now in glad holiday apparel, was
joyously, though somewhat vain gloriously, sailing round among the
widely separated ships on the ground, previous to pointing her prow for home.
The three men at her mast head wore long streamers of narrow red bunting at their
hats. From the stern a whaleboat was suspended, bottom down, and hanging
captive from the bow sprit was seen the long lower jaw of the last whale they
had slain. Signals, ensons, and jacks of all colors were flying from her rigging
on every side. Sideways lashed in each of her three basketed tops were two
barrels of sperm, above which in her top mass cross trees you saw slender
breakers of the same precious fluid, and nailed to her main truck was a brazen lamp.
As was afterwards learned, the Bachelor had met with the most surprising
success, all the more wonderful, for that while cruising in these same seas,
numerous other vessels had gone entire months without securing a single fish.
Not only had barrels of beef and bread been given away to make room for the far
more valuable sperm, but additional supplemental casks had been bartered for
from the ship she had met, and these were stowed along the deck and in the
captains and officers stateooms. Even the cabin table itself had been knocked
into kindling wood, and the cabin mess dined off the broadhead of an oil butt
lashed down to the floor for a centerpiece. In the folks, the sailors
had actually cocked and pitched their chests and filled them. It was
humorously added that the cook had clapped ahead on his largest boiler and
filled it. That the steward had plugged his spare coffee pot and filled it. That
the harpooners had headed the sockets of their iron and filled them. that indeed
everything was filled with sperm except the captain's pantaloon's pockets and
those he reserved to thrust his hands into in self-complacent testimony of his
entire satisfaction.
As this glad ship of good luck bore down upon the moody peekquad, the barbarian
sound of enormous drums came from her folil, and drawing still nearer, a crowd
of her men were seen standing round her huge tripods, which covered with the
parchment-like poke or stomach skin of the black fish, gave forth a loud roar
to every stroke of the clenched hands of the crew. On the quarter deck, the mates
and harpooners were dancing with the olive hued girls who had eloped with
them from the Polynesian isles. While suspended in an ornamented boat, firmly
secured a loft between the formast and the main mast, three Long Island negroes
with glittering fiddle bows of whale ivory were presiding over the hilarious
jig. Meanwhile, others of the ship's company were tumultuously busy at the
masonry of the triworks from which the huge pots had been removed. You would
have almost thought they were pulling down the cursed bastile, such wild cries
they raised, as the now useless brick and mortar were being hurled into the sea.
Lord and master over all this scene. The captain stood ereck on the ship's
elevated quarter deck, so that the whole rejoicing drama was full before him, and
seemed merely contrived for his own individual diversion.
And Ahab, he too was standing on his quarter deck, shaggy and black with a
stubborn gloom. And as the two ships crossed each other's wakes, one all
jubilations for things past, the other all forodings as to things to come,
their two captains in themselves impersonated the whole striking contrast
of the scene. "Come aboard! Come aboard!" cried the gay bachelor's
commander, lifting a glass and a bottle in the air. "Hast seen the white whale?"
gritted Ahab in reply. No, only heard of him, but don't believe in him at all,
said the other good humoredly. Come aboard.
Thou art too damn jolly. Sail on. Hast lost any men. Not enough to speak of.
Two islanders, that's all. But come aboard, old Hardy. Come along. I'll soon
take that black from your brow. Come along, will you? Mary's the play. A full
ship and homeward bound.
How wondrous familiar is a fool, muttered Ahab, and then aloud, Thou art
a full ship, and homeward bound, thou sayest. Well, then call me an empty ship
and outward bound, so go thy ways, and I will mine. Forward there, set all sail,
and keep her to the wind."
And thus, while the one ship went cheerily before the breeze, the others
stubbornly fought against it. And so the two vessels parted, the crew of the
Peekquad looking with grave lingering glances toward the receding bachelor,
but the bachelor's men never heeding their gaze for the lively realry they were in.
And as Ahab, leaning over the taffrail, eyed the homewardbound craft, he took
from his pocket a small vial of sand, and then looking from the ship to the
vial, seemed thereby bringing two remote associations together, for that vial was
filled with Nantucket soundings.